<book xmlns:xxi="http://orbeon.org/oxf/xml/xinclude" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ev="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml-events" xmlns:xforms="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xbl="http://www.w3.org/ns/xbl" xmlns:exforms="http://www.exforms.org/exf/1-0" xmlns:pipeline="java:org.orbeon.oxf.processor.pipeline.PipelineFunctionLibrary" xmlns:fr="http://orbeon.org/oxf/xml/form-runner" xmlns:xxforms="http://orbeon.org/oxf/xml/xforms">
    <details>
        <title>The Terror</title>
        <author>Dan Simmons</author>
        <language>en</language>
        <link/>
        <rating/>
        <publication-year/>
        <review>&lt;b&gt;From Publishers Weekly&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br clear="none"/&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Starred Review.&lt;/i&gt;  Hugo-winner Simmons (&lt;i&gt;Olympos&lt;/i&gt;)
brings the horrific trials and tribulations of arctic exploration
vividly to life in this beautifully written historical, which injects a
note of supernatural horror into the 1840s Franklin expedition and its
doomed search for the Northwest Passage. Sir John Franklin, the leader
of the expedition and captain of the &lt;i&gt;Erebus&lt;/i&gt;, is an aging fool. Francis Crozier, his second in command and captain of the &lt;i&gt;Terror&lt;/i&gt;,
is a competent sailor, but embittered after years of seeing lesser men
with better connections given preferment over him. With their two ships
quickly trapped in pack ice, their voyage is a disaster from start to
finish. Some men perish from disease, others from the cold, still
others from botulism traced to tinned food purchased from the lowest
bidder. Madness, mutiny and cannibalism follow. And then there's the
monstrous creature from the ice, the thing like a polar bear but many
times larger, possessed of a dark and vicious intelligence. This
complex tale should find many devoted readers and add significantly to
Simmons's already considerable reputation. &lt;i&gt;(Jan.)&lt;/i&gt; &lt;br clear="none"/&gt;&lt;div style="text-align: left;"&gt;Copyright © Reed Business Information, a division of Reed Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.
  
&lt;/div&gt;</review>
        <image filename="The Terror.jpg" mediatype="image/jpeg" size="15773">http://localhost:8080/orbeon/fr/service/exist/crud/orbeon/bookshelf/data/e8bfd3ba63fa12a8b59cdd5c08369a35/e9f827e57410b51359a5d82351ab1b9b.jpg</image>
    </details>
    <notes>
        <note/>
    </notes>
</book>