<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252"?>
<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline" xmlns:xforms="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms"
        xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xxforms="http://orbeon.org/oxf/xml/xforms"
        xmlns:oxf="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/processors" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <header>
        <title>Changes in Version 2.8</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>XForms</title>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        It is now possible to have multiple <code>&lt;xforms:alert></code> in an
                        XForms control. They will be all kept by the XForms engine and transformed
                        into <code>&lt;f:alert></code>. The theme can then decide which one should
                        be displayed. The default theme displays all the alerts.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        You can use multiple <code>&lt;xforms:alert></code> for internationalization
                        by adding on each <code>&lt;xforms:alert></code> an <code>xml:lang</code>
                        attribute (e.g. <code>xml:lang="en"</code>, <code>xml:lang="fr"</code>) and
                        selecting in your theme the appropriate message to display for the current
                        user based on his preferred language.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        XForms schema validation can now be used to <a
                        href="http://tinyurl.com/5l7q8">validate attributes in the XForms
                        instance</a>. Note that the <code>xxforms:valid="false"</code> attribute is
                        still only added on invalid elements in the XForms instance. The XForms
                        engine does not annotate the XForms instance for invalid attributes.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        Instance nodes of type <code>xs:date</code> and <code>xs:time</code> bound
                        to an XForms input control are rendered with an <a
                        href="http://tinyurl.com/6wu6p">appropriate date or time widget</a>. You
                        set the type of an instance node with a <code>&lt;xforms:bind
                        nodeset="/path/to/your/node" type="xs:date"/></code> in your XForms model.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        As the XForms engine validates the XForms instance with a schema and
                        evaluates the model item properties on the instance, it annotates the
                        instance with attributes using the <code>xxforms</code> prefix. For
                        instance, if an element is validated, an attribute
                        <code>xxforms:valid="true|false"</code> is added on the element. In previous
                        versions of OPS you could override the value set by the
                        XForms engine in the MVC model or MVC view by modifying the value of those
                        attributes in the instance. As the instance can be modified in the MVC
                        model and view, the model item properties are reevaluated and the instance
                        revalidated with the schema after the MVC view, in the epilogue. At that
                        point, for example, if there is a <code>xxforms:valid="false"</code>
                        attribute on a given element, but validation with the schema and model
                        item properties returns "true", the XForms engine does not know if the
                        content of the element was modified in the MVC model or view and the error
                        corrected (in which case the element should be considered valid), or if the
                        <code>xxforms:valid="false"</code> was added by the MVC model or view to
                        tell the XForms engine that this element is invalid (in which case the
                        element should be considered invalid).
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        To solve this problem, starting with OPS 2.8, you cannot
                        override the annotations added by the XForms engine on the instance. Those
                        annotations should be considered read-only. Instead, to instruct the XForms
                        engine that a given node is invalid, use the method described in the <a
                        href="reference-xforms-ng#custom-validation">Custom Validation</a> section of
                        the XForms reference. The benefit of this method is that it does not require
                        the use of proprietary XForms extensions and that it can be used on elements
                        as well as attributes.
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Move to ObjectWeb and Product Name</title>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    Orbeon <a href="http://www.orbeon.com/company/pr-objectweb">joined the ObjectWeb
                    consortium</a> and the project is now hosted on the <a
                    href="http://forge.objectweb.org/projects/ops/">ObjectWeb Forge</a>.
                </li>
                <li>
                    The name of the product is now written Orbeon PresentationServer (in one word).
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Performance Improvements</title>
            <p>
                Memory usage has been improved, which leads to significant performance improvements
                under heavy load or when the JVM is running with a relatively small heap, as the JVM
                spends less time doing garbage collection. Our testing shows performance
                improvement that range from 5% to 20% over version 2.7.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Miscellaneous Bug Fixes</title>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <a href="http://tinyurl.com/5eq9d">XUpdate removing attributes and namespace
                    declarations</a> &#8213; When using the <code>&lt;xu:xupdate></code> instruction to
                    update the content of an element, the existing attributes and namespaces of the
                    element were incorrectly removed.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="http://tinyurl.com/47eqg">XForms xhtml:onclick attribute</a> &#8213;
                    The attribute xhtml:onclick on XForms submit control was ignored.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="http://tinyurl.com/5hqzy">Rendering issues of the documentation under
                    Safari</a> &#8213; Those issues have been solved.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Other bugs have been fixed relative to the URL generator, Request generator,
                    HTTP serializer, and server-side forwards following a file upload.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
