<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252"?>
<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline" xmlns:xforms="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xxforms="http://orbeon.org/oxf/xml/xforms" xmlns:oxf="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/processors" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <header>
        <title>Changes in Version 2.6</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section>
            <a name="2.6-xforms"/>
            <title>XForms</title>
            <section>
                <title>XForms Upload</title>
                <p>
                    The XForms Upload control has been fixed. It comes with an <a href="/xforms-upload/">example</a>
                    and is documented in the <a href="/doc/reference-xforms-ng#upload">XForms reference
                    documentation</a>.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>XForms Conditionals</title>
                <p>
                   Two new extension controls provide a mechanism to selectively enable markup and other XForms controls depending of
                   the values stored in the XForms instance. The syntax is modeled after the XSLT language:
                   <code>if</code> and <code>choose/when/otherwise</code>. See the <a href="reference-xforms-ng#conditionals">XForms Conditionals</a>
                   documentation for more information.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Itemset Support</title>
                <p>
                    The XForms element <code>&lt;itemset></code> is now supported. You can use it in conjunction with
                    XForms selection controls (<code>&lt;xforms:select</code> and <code>&lt;xforms:select1></code>) when
                    you want the list of items the end-user has to pick from to come from the instance, instead of being
                    listed in view. For more details, see the <a href=" reference-xforms-ng#xforms-controls">XForms
                    controls</a> documentation and the <a href="/xforms-controls/">XFormsControls</a> example.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Support for ref Attribute on Label, Alert, Help, and Hint</title>
                <p>
                    You can now use the <code>ref</code> attribute on
                    <code>&lt;xforms:label></code>, <code>&lt;xforms:alert></code>,
                    <code>&lt;xforms:help></code>, and <code>&lt;xforms:hint></code> to have the
                    displayed message come from the instance instead of being specified in the
                    view. For more details, see the <a
                    href="reference-xforms-ng#label-alert-help-hint">Label, Alert, Help, and
                    Hint</a> documentation.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Support for ref Attribute on Submit Controls</title>
                <p>
                    You can now bind a submit control (<code>&lt;xforms:submit></code>) to a
                    node in the instance with the <code>ref</code> attribute. If you do so, the
                    submit control will only be displayed if the node it is bound to is
                    relevant. This way you can define in the XForms model rules that specify
                    when a submit control is to be displayed.
                </p>
            </section>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-binary"/>
        <section>
            <title>Standard Representation of Binary and Text Documents</title>
            <p>
                In OPS <a href="reference-xpl-pipelines">XPL and pipelines</a>
                only deal with XML documents. In order to handle non-XML data such as binary and
                text documents in pipelines, OPS defines <a
                href="reference-formats">two standard XML document formats</a> to embed binary
                and text documents within an XML infoset. This solution has the benefit of
                keeping XPL simple by limiting it to pure XML infosets, while allowing XPL to
                conveniently manipulate any binary and text document.
            </p>
            <p>
                These document formats are widely used by processors such as the <a
                href="processors-generators-url">URL generator</a>, the <a
                href="processors-serializers-http">HTTP serializer</a>, the <a
                href="processors-messaging-email">Email processor</a>, and <a
                href="processors-converters">converters</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-body"/>
        <section>
            <title>Improved Request Body and Uploaded Files Support</title>
            <p>
                It was possible in the past with the <a
                href="processors-generators-request">Request generator</a> to obtain
                the request body, which was automatically parsed as XML. This behavior has now
                been changed. It is instead possible to obtain the request body as
                <code>xs:anyURI</code> or <code>xs:base64Binary</code> (<a
                href="reference-formats#binary-documents">standard binary document format</a>).
                Parsing may then be done using the <a
                href="processors-generators-url">URL generator</a>. In addition, the
                body can now be read several times. This change brings consistency with the
                handling of uploaded files, and the support for binary files thoughout
                OPS.
            </p>
            <p>
                In a related change, the <a
                href="processors-generators-request">Request generator</a> now
                supports specifying whether uploaded files or the request body must be generated
                as <code>xs:anyURI</code> or <code>xs:base64Binary</code>.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-url"/>
        <section>
            <title>URL Generator</title>
            <section>
                <title>Binary Mode</title>
                <p>
                    The <a href="processors-generators-url">URL generator</a> now supports streaming binary files
                    encoded with Base64. The <a href="/xforms-upload/">XForms Upload example</a>, among others,
                    illustrates this capability.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Text Mode</title>
                <p>
                    The <a href="processors-generators-url">URL generator</a> now supports reading text files. The <a
                    href="/employees/">Employees example</a> illustrates this capability.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>XML Content Type</title>
                <p>
                    The <a href="processors-generators-url">URL generator</a> now
                    correctly detects as XML the following content types:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><code>application/xml</code>, the recommended content type for XML</li>
                    <li><code>text/xml</code>, the now deprecated content type for XML</li>
                    <li>content types ending with <code>+xml</code> such as <code>image/svg+xml</code></li>
                </ul>
            </section>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-serializer"/>
        <section>
            <title>Serializers</title>
            <section>
                <title>New Serializer Architecture</title>
                <p>
                    The pre-2.6 serializer architecture did not clearly separate the following
                    concerns:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Conversion of XML documents to a character or byte stream.</li>
                    <li>
                        Sending a character or text stream to a particular destination, such as
                        a web browser through HTTP, or a file on disk.
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    The new architecture introduces <a
                    href="processors-converters">converters</a> in charge of the first task, and
                    plain <a href="processors-serializers">serializers</a> in charge of the
                    second task. It relies on the <a href="reference-formats">standard
                    representation</a> for binary and texts documents.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Backward compatibility for existing serializers is kept, but it is
                    recommended to use the new converters and serializers whenever possible.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>HTTP Serializer</title>
                <p>
                    A new serializer, the <a href="processors-serializers-http">HTTP serializer</a>, supports decoding
                    of binary or text data, and sending the resulting stream to an HTTP client. The <a
                    href="/xforms-upload/">XForms Upload example</a> illustrates this capability. The HTTP serializer
                    can be used for example in conjunction with <a href="processors-converters">converters</a> and the
                    URL generator.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The <a href="processors-serializers-http">HTTP serializer</a>
                    uses the recommended <code>application/xml</code> content type by default
                    rather than <code>text/xml</code>.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>New Configuration Parameters</title>
                <p>
                    The <code>omit-xml-declaration</code> and <code>standalone</code>
                    configuration parameters of the <a
                    href="processors-converters#xml-converter">XML converter</a> are now
                    documented. The <code>cache-control/use-local-cache</code> configuration
                    parameter of the <a href="processors-serializers-http">HTTP
                    serializer</a> is now documented.
                </p>
            </section>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-examples"/>
        <section>
            <title>Examples</title>
            <section>
                <title>BizDoc Application Changes</title>
                <p>
                    The data access layer of the BizDoc application has been refactored to support
                    the following backends:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <b>XML databases:</b> XML documents are accessed through the XML:DB
                        processors. Currently, the backend assumes the built-in open source eXist
                        database.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <b>SQL databases:</b> XML documents are accessed as a text or native XML
                        format.
                    </li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    It is now possible to visualize each document as XML from the user interface.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>New "Employees" Example</title>
                <p>
                    The new <a href="/employees/">Employees example application</a> illustrates the following aspects
                    of OPS:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>CRUD operations, paging and sorting with a SQL backend</li>
                    <li>XForms controls and validation with XML Schema</li>
                    <li>XForms upload control</li>
                    <li>Reading plain text files</li>
                    <li>Using the Java processor</li>
                    <li>Exporting Comma-Separated Values (CSV) files</li>
                    <li>Exporting and importing Excel files</li>
                    <li>Calling and implementing Web Service</li>
                    <li>Authentication (login / logout) and roles</li>
                    <li>LDAP access</li>
                </ul>
            </section>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-pageflow"/>
        <section>
            <title>Page Flow</title>
            <p>
                XSLT views in <a href="reference-page-flow">Page Flow</a> can now access the
                XForms instance using <code>document('input:instance')</code> or
                <code>doc('input:instance')</code>. In the past, it was often necessary for the
                model to aggregate its output with the XForms instance to make both documents
                accessible from the view.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-email"/>
        <section>
            <title>Email Processor</title>
            <p>
                The <a href="processors-messaging-email">Email processor</a> features the
                following improvements:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <b>Multipart hierarchy:</b> it is possible to have multiple levels of
                    multipart messages.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Binary attachments:</b> binary files such as images and PDF files can be
                    attached to an email.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Dynamic attachments:</b> attachments can be generated dynamically. It is
                    for example possible to attach a dynamically generated chart or PDF file.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Character encoding:</b> character encoding can be specified for text content.
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                In addition, property naming has been revisted. The <code>test-smtp-host</code>
                and <code>test-to</code> replace the deprecated <code>host</code> and
                <code>forceto</code> properties.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-custom"/>
        <section>
            <title>Custom Processors</title>
            <p>
                There is a new facility to declare custom processors that does not involve
                modifying the original <code>processors.xml</code> file. To do this, create a
                file called <code>oxf:/config/custom-processors.xml</code>. Its format is the
                same as the original <code>processors.xml</code>.
            </p>
            <p>
                The <code>Processor</code> API has been enhanced to provide access to the inputs
                and outputs actually connected (as opposed to just those that have been
                declared). This provides access to optional inputs and outputs. Please refer to
                the Javadoc for the <code>Processor</code> class for more information, as well
                as the <code>ListInputs</code> unit test.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-webdav"/>
        <section>
            <title>WebDAV Resource Manager</title>
            <p>
                A <a href="reference-resource-managers#webdav">WebDAV resource manager</a> is
                now included. It supports basic authentication.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="2.6-java5"/>
        <section>
            <title>J2SE 5.0 Support</title>
            <p>
                The source code of OPS now compiles with Java 5.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
