<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline" xmlns:xforms="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms">
    <header>
        <title>Command Line Applications</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>
                You can use OPS to build standalone command-line applications running pipelines. Use
                cases include: creating a hardcopy of a web site, importing or exporting XML data to
                and from a relational database, testing pipelines, automating repetitive operations
                on XML files (selection, transformation, aggregation, etc.). OPS becomes your "XML
                toolbox".
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Command Line Interface</title>
            <p>
                OPS ships with a command line interface (CLI). The easiest way to run it is to use
                the executable <code>cli-ops.jar</code> file and pass it a pipeline file:
            </p>
            <source>java -jar cli-ops.jar pipeline.xpl</source>
            <p>
                In this case, a pipeline can use relative URLs, or, if using absolute URLs, can use
                either the <code>file:</code> protocol to access files or, equivalently, the
                <code>oxf:</code> protocol.
            </p>
            <p>
                Sometimes, it is better to group files under a resources <i>sandbox</i> addressed by
                the <code>oxf:</code> protocol. This is the standard way of accessing resources
                (files) within web applications, but it is also useful with command-line
                applications. In such cases, specify a resource manager root directory with the
                <code>-r</code> option, for example:
            </p>
            <source>java -jar cli-ops.jar -r . oxf:/pipeline.xpl</source>
            <p>
                or:
            </p>
            <source>java -jar cli-ops.jar -r C:/my-example oxf:/pipeline.xpl</source>
            <p>
                When specifying a resource manager root directory, it is mandatory to use a protocol
                and an absolute path within the sandbox, as shown above.
            </p>
            <note>
                <p>
                    OPS's jar file (<code>cli-ops.jar</code>) is executable via the <code>java
                    -jar</code> mechanism. However, it depends on a number of libraries that must be
                    in the 'lib' directory beneath the directory containing
                    <code>cli-ops.jar</code>. It is recommended to expand the WAR file, and refer
                    to the <code>cli-ops.jar</code> file under the WAR file's <i>WEB-INF</i>
                    directory.
                </p>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Examples</title>
            <p>
                OPS comes with simple examples of command-line applications under the
                <code>src/examples/cli</code> directory. To run those examples, from a command
                prompt, enter either one of the subdirectories and run the <code>java</code> command
                following the explanations above, for example, from the <code>simple</code>
                directory:
            </p>
            <source>java -jar /path/to/orbeon-war/WEB-INF/cli-ops.jar stdout.xpl</source>
            <p>
                or, from the <code>transform</code> directory:
            </p>
            <source>java -jar /path/to/orbeon-war/WEB-INF/cli-ops.jar transform.xpl</source>
            <p>
                Notice that those two example pipelines use serializers, for example:
            </p>
            <xml-source>
                <p:config xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline"
                          xmlns:oxf="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/processors">

                    <p:processor name="oxf:xslt">
                        <p:input name="data" href="foo.xml"/>
                        <p:input name="config" href="foo.xsl"/>
                        <p:output name="data" id="result"/>
                    </p:processor>

                    <p:processor name="oxf:xml-serializer">
                        <p:input name="config">
                            <config/>
                        </p:input>
                        <p:input name="data" href="#result"/>
                    </p:processor>

                </p:config>
            </xml-source>
            <p>
                It is important to note that, when running from within a servlet or portlet
                environment, serializers send their data to the web client, such as a web browser.
                When running from a command-line environment, serializers output data to the
                standard output.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
