<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004-2007 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline" xmlns:xforms="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms">
    <header>
        <title>Error Page and Error Dialog</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Rationale</title>
            <p>
                During development or at runtime, errors can occur in Orbeon Forms. There are two main circumstances
                handled by Orbeon Forms:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Error page.</b> Errors occurring when producing an entire page on the server. In this
                        case, Orbeon Forms attempts to display an error page.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Error dialog.</b> Errors occurring in XForms pages when processing Ajax requests. In this
                        case, Orbeon Forms attempts to display an error dialog within the page.
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                Orbeon Forms provides defaults for the error page and error dialog. The default error dialog looks as
                follows with Orbeon Forms 3.6:
            </p>
            <img src="../apps/doc/images/home-changes-35-ajax-error-1.png" alt="Ajax error dialog"/>
            <p>
                An initially collapsed section containing details of the error useful to the developer:
            </p>
            <img src="../apps/doc/images/home-changes-35-ajax-error-2.png" alt="Ajax error dialog"/>
            <p>
                Advanced developers can configure the appearance of the error messages. This is discussed in the
                following sections. In most cases, it is expected that overriding CSS defintions will be enough. Only
                in more advanced cases should overriding the XSLT stylesheet, XPL pipelines or even reconfiguring the
                error processors be necessary.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>High-Level Architecture</title>
            <p>
                An error occurring during an HTTP request is handled by the <i>error processor</i> associated, in
                <code>web.xml</code>, with the servlet handling the request. For more information about error
                processors, please refer to the <a href="integration-packaging#error-configuration">Packaging and
                Deployment</a> documentation.
            </p>
            <p>
                The default error processor is the <code>oxf:pipeline</code> processor, which runs
                <code>oxf:/config/error.xpl</code> for entire pages, and
                <code>oxf:/ops/xforms/xforms-server-error.xpl</code> for Ajax requests. These two pipelines are located
                within <code>orbeon-resources-private.jar</code>.
            </p>
            <p>
                It is unlikely that you will need to change the configuration of the error processors.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Default Error Pipeline</title>
            <p>
                The default error pipeline, <code>oxf:/config/error.xpl</code>, performs the following tasks:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        It uses the <code>oxf:exception</code> processor to serialize Java exception data to XML.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        It formats an error page into an XHTML document using <code>oxf:/config/error.xsl</code>.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        The error page is then procesed by the default theme, <code>oxf:/config/theme-plain.xsl</code>.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        The result is serialized to the client browser with an HTTP status code of 500.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        The client just displays the resulting HTML page.
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                It is unlikely that you will need to modify this pipeline.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Ajax Error Pipeline</title>
            <p>
                The default Ajax error pipeline, <code>oxf:/ops/xforms/xforms-server-error.xpl</code>, performs the
                following tasks:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        It uses the <code>oxf:exception</code> processor to serialize Java exception data to XML.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        It formats the error dialog content into an XHTML fragment using
                        <code>oxf:/config/error.xsl</code>.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        The result is converted into serialized HTML embeeded within an XML Ajax response.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        The result is serialized to the client browser, which then displays the content within a
                        dialog.
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                It is unlikely that you will need to modify this pipeline.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title><code>error.xsl</code> and <code>error.css</code></title>
            <p>
                The <code>oxf:/config/error.xsl</code> stylesheet is used to format error pages as well as error
                dialogs. This stylesheet contains:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        A top-level template displaying an entire error page.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        A template named <code>format-xforms-error-panel-body</code> which formats the error panel
                        message body that appears in the error dialog.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        Named templates, <code>format-message</code>, <code>format-orbeon-call-stack</code>,
                        <code>format-java-stack-trace</code>, and <code>format-message</code> which are shared between
                        the error page and error dialog.
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                If the default layout of the error page or error dialog does not fit your application, you can change it
                by overriding this stylesheet under your application's <code>RESOURCES/config/error.xsl</code>.
            </p>
            <p>
                <code>error.xsl</code> makes use of the <code>error.css</code> stylesheet located under
                <code>oxf:/config/theme/error.css</code>. If you just want to change the appearance of the error page
                and/or dialog, you can override these CSS definitions in your application.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
