<!--
    Copyright (C) 2007 Orbeon, Inc.

    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the
    GNU Lesser General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version
    2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY;
    without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
    See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details.

    The full text of the license is available at http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html
-->
<books>
    <book>
        <title>Don Quixote de la Mancha</title>
        <author>Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra</author>
        <language>es</language>
        <link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don_Quixote</link>
        <rating>5</rating>

        <notes>The book tells the story of Alonso Quixano, a man who has read so many stories about brave errant knights that, in a half-mad and confused state, he believes himself to be a knight, re-names himself Don Quixote de la Mancha, and sets out to fight injustice in the name of his beloved maiden Aldonsa, or as he knows her in his mind, Dulcinea del Toboso.</notes>
    </book>
    <book>
        <title>Jacques le fataliste et son maître</title>
        <author>Denis Diderot</author>
        <language>fr</language>
        <link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_le_fataliste_et_son_ma%C3%AEtre</link>

        <rating>5</rating>
        <notes>Ce roman complexe et déconcertant — sans doute l'œuvre de Diderot la plus commentée — puise pour partie son inspiration dans l'ouvrage de Laurence Sterne, Vie et opinions de Tristram Shandy paru quelques années auparavant (1759-1763).</notes>
    </book>
    <book>
        <title>Childhood's End</title>
        <author>Arthur C. Clarke</author>
        <language>en</language>

        <link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Childhood%27s_End</link>
        <rating>5</rating>
        <notes>Childhood's End deals with humanity's transformation and integration into an interplanetary hive mind. The book also touches on the issues of the Occult, man's inability to live in a utopian society, and cruelty to animals, as well as the cliché of being the last man on Earth.</notes>
    </book>
    <book>
        <title>The Demon-Haunted World</title>
        <author>Carl Sagan</author>

        <language>en</language>
        <link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Demon-Haunted_World</link>
        <rating>5</rating>
        <notes>Sagan states that when new ideas are offered for consideration, they should be tested by means of skeptical thinking, and should stand up to rigorous questioning.</notes>
    </book>
</books>