<!--
    Copyright (C) 2005 TAO Consulting Pte Ltd

    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the
    GNU Lesser General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version
    2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY;
    without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
    See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details.

    The full text of the license is available at http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html
-->
<example-descriptor>
	<title>PDF Upload Example</title>
	<xi:include href="example-descriptor-files.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>
	<description>
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <p>
                You can upload PDF Files with the form.<br/> The uploaded PDF gets processed by the
                fromPDF processor and Meta-Information and/or Text gets extracted.<br/>
                The examples posts the information back to the browser. Typically you would
                process that information in your database or fulltext search.
            </p>
            <p>
                The PDF extraction processor will take an PDF file as input and extract meta
                information and or text from the PDF. The extracted structure can be used by fulltext
                search or a content management system to identify the exact location of content items.
                The processor makes use of the PDFBox Library http://www.pdfbox.org.
            </p>
            <p>
                The processor allows 5 modes of operation. In mode one only the meta data and the
                bookmarks with title and page number but no text is extracted. In mode two meta data,
                bookmarks and text is extracted. In mode three meta data and text broken down into pages
                is extracted. In mode 4 only the meta data gets extracted (if any). In mode five first
                an extraction of bookmarks with text is attempted. If there are no bookmarks a fallback
                to pages is performed.
            </p>
            <p>
                If the file containes errors, then the operation might not complete. Most errors are
                captured and will lead to the insertion of an &lt;error&gt; tag. If the input file is
                fundamentally broken no output will be displayed (however the processor returns an empty
                &lt;PDFDocument /&gt; entry.
            </p>
        </div>
	</description>
</example-descriptor>
