<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline" xmlns:xforms="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms">
    <header>
        <title>Welcome</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Welcome to the Orbeon PresentationServer User Guide!</p>
            <p>
                Orbeon PresentationServer (OPS) is an open source J2EE-based platform for
                XML-centric web applications. OPS is built around XHTML, XForms, XSLT, XML
                pipelines, and Web Services, which makes it ideal for applications that capture,
                process and present XML data.
            </p>
            <p>
                Unlike other popular web application frameworks like Struts or WebWork that are
                based on Java objects and JSP, OPS is based on XML documents and XML technologies.
                This leads to an architecture better suited for the tasks of capturing, processing,
                and presenting information in XML format, and often does not require writing any
                Java code at all to implement your presentation layer.
            </p>
            <p>
                OPS is built around Orbeon's optimized <a href="reference-xpl-pipelines">XPL
                engine</a>, a mature, high-performance XML pipeline engine for processing XML data.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Purpose of the User Guide</title>

            <p>
                The purpose of this guide is to get users acquainted with the fundamental concepts
                of PresentationServer: XML processors and XML pipelines, the XML Pipeline
                Definition Language (XPL), XForms, the Page Flow Controller (PFC), and
                PresentationServer's built-in XML processors. It is highly recommended to quickly
                get to the <a href="/doc/pages/Tutorial.pdf">Tutorial</a> to get started with
                developing applications with PresentationServer.
            </p>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Prerequisites</title>

            <p>
                This guide should be accessible to anyone with some experience
                developing simple Web applications. It is helpful to understand
                the basics of XML and Extensible Stylesheet Language
                Transformations (XSLT) before reading this documentation. For
                more information, consult the following sources as a starting
                point:
            </p>

            <ul>
                <li>
                    <a href="http://www.w3.org/XML/">XML</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="http://www.w3.org/Style/XSL/">XSLT</a>
                </li>
            </ul>

            <p>
                In addition to online resources, many books about these 
                technologies are available in printed form.
            </p>

        </section>

    </body>
</document>
