<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline">
    <header>
        <title>Other Processors</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <a name="file-processor"/>
        <section>
            <title>File Processor</title>
            <p>
                The File Processor allows you to delete files on disk. In the future, it may be
                enhanced to provide more actions such as renaming files, moving files, etc.
            </p>
            <section>
                <title>Inputs and Outputs</title>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Type</th>
                        <th>Name</th>
                        <th>Purpose</th>
                        <th>Mandatory</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td align="center">Input</td>
                        <td>
                            <code>config</code>
                        </td>
                        <td>Configuration</td>
                        <td align="center">Yes</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
                <p>
                    The <code>config</code> input contains a single <code>delete</code> element. In
                    turn, it contains a <code>file</code> element which specifies the name of the
                    file to delete, and an optional <code>directory</code> element containing a base
                    directory against which the file name is resolved.
                </p>
                <p>
                    If the file exists and is writable, the processor attempts to delete it.
                    Otherwise, no attempt is made. If an attempt is made and deleting fails, an
                    exception is raised.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example</title>
                <p>
                    The following is an example of a pipeline running the File Processor in order to
                    delete a file called <code>SomeImpossibleFileName.jpg</code> present under the
                    <code>C:/TEMP</code> directory.
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:config xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline"
                        xmlns:oxf="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/processors">
                        <p:processor name="oxf:file-processor">
                            <p:input name="config">
                                <config>
                                    <delete>
                                        <file>SomeImpossibleFileName.jpg</file>
                                        <directory>C:/TEMP</directory>
                                    </delete>
                                </config>
                            </p:input>
                        </p:processor>
                    </p:config>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
        </section>
        <a name="resource-server"/>
        <section>
            <title>Resource Server</title>
            <p>
                The Resource Server serves resources such as images, CSS stylesheet or other static
                files. Resources are sent to the HTTP response untouched, and the HTTP cache
                control headers are set.
            </p>
            <section>
                <title>Config Input</title>
                <p>
                    The <code>config</code> input contains a single <code>url</code> element
                    containing an absolute URL. The URL can be any URL supported by your platform,
                    in particular URLs with the following protocols:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li><code>file</code></li>
                    <li><code>http</code></li>
                    <li><code>oxf</code> (to access OPS resources)</li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    The Resource Server supports the deprecated use of a <code>config</code> input
                    containing a single <code>path</code> element representing the absolute Resource
                    Manager path of the file to serve. Since the <code>url</code> element also
                    allows to access to OPS resources, it is recommended to use it
                    instead of <code>path</code>.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>MIME Types Input</title>
                <p>
                    The <code>mime-types</code> input contains a list of patterns and <link
                    href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/">MIME Media Types</link>.
                    This mapping list determines which <code>content-type</code> header to send to
                    the browser. The patterns are case-insensitive. OPS is bundled
                    with a default mapping file under the URL <code>oxf:/oxf/mime-types.xml</code>.
                    You can create your own mapping to suit your needs. The RelaxNG schema is
                    provided below.
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <element name="mime-types" xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
                        datatypeLibrary="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes">
                        <oneOrMore>
                            <element name="mime-type">
                                <element name="name">
                                    <data type="string"/>
                                </element>
                                <oneOrMore>
                                    <element name="pattern">
                                        <data type="string"/>
                                    </element>
                                </oneOrMore>
                            </element>
                        </oneOrMore>
                    </element>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example</title>
                <p>
                    The example below shows the Resource Server configured to send a PNG image file
                    with the appropriate MIME type.
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:processor name="oxf:resource-server">
                        <p:input name="mime-types">
                            <mime-types>
                                <mime-type>
                                    <name>image/png</name>
                                    <pattern>*.png</pattern>
                                </mime-type>
                            </mime-types>
                        </p:input>
                        <p:input name="config">
                            <url>oxf:/images/logo.png</url>
                        </p:input>
                    </p:processor>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
        </section>
        <a name="identity-processor"/>
        <section>
            <title>Identity Processor</title>
            <p>
                The Identity processor is one of the simplest processors of OPS: it
                simply copies the content of its <code>data</code> input to its <code>data</code>
                output. While at first this doesn't seem like a very useful feature, it actually can
                be very convenient, for example in the following scenarios.
            </p>
            <section>
                <title>Embedding XML Documents</title>
                <p>
                    XML documents can be embedded within pipeline inputs. When you want the same
                    document to be passed to the input of multiple processors in a pipeline, instead
                    of duplicating it and embedding it in every input, you can use the Identity
                    processor: embed the document in the <code>data</code> input of the Identity
                    processor, assign an id to the output of the Identity processor, and reference
                    that id from other inputs you want to feed with that document.
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:config xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline">
                        <comment> Embed employee data </comment>
                        <p:processor name="oxf:identity">
                            <p:input name="data">
                                <employees>
                                    <employee>
                                        <first-name>Joe</first-name>
                                        <last-name>Dalton</last-name>
                                    </employee>
                                    <employee>
                                        <first-name>Averell</first-name>
                                        <last-name>Dalton</last-name>
                                    </employee>
                                </employees>
                            </p:input>
                            <p:output name="data" id="employees"/>
                        </p:processor>
                        <comment> Apply a first transformation on the employee data </comment>
                        <p:processor name="oxf:xslt">
                            <p:input name="config" href="oxf:/transform-1.xsl"/>
                            <p:input name="data" href="#employees"/>
                            <p:output name="data" id="result-1"/>
                        </p:processor>
                        <comment> Apply a second transformation on the same employee data </comment>
                        <p:processor name="oxf:xslt">
                            <p:input name="config" href="oxf:/transform-2.xsl"/>
                            <p:input name="data" href="#employees"/>
                            <p:output name="data" id="result-2"/>
                        </p:processor>
                        <comment> ... </comment>
                    </p:config>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Aggregating and Modifying Documents</title>
                <p>
                    Pipeline inputs support aggregation with the <code>aggregate()</code> function,
                    as well as the XPointer syntax. The Identity processor can then be used to
                    aggregate or otherwise modify existing documents in a pipeline, for example
                    before sending a result to a pipeline output.
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:config xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline">
                        <p:param type="output" name="data"/>
                        <comment> ... </comment>
                        <comment> Assuming the XSLT transformations in the previous example, transform the two results and send them to the data output </comment>
                        <p:processor name="oxf:identity">
                            <p:input name="data" href="aggregate('result', #result-1#xpointer(/*/*), , #result-2#xpointer(/*/*[position() *lt; 10]))"/>
                            <p:output name="data" ref="data"/>
                        </p:processor>
                    </p:config>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
        </section>
        <a name="debug-processor"/>
        <section>
            <title>Debug Processor</title>
            <p>
                The Debug processor logs XML documents using the <link
                href="http://jakarta.apache.org/log4j/docs/">Log4j</link> library. It has 2 inputs:
                <code>data</code> contains the XML document to log, and <code>config</code> has a
                <code>config</code> root element that contains a message typically be used to
                describe the XML document. The <code>data</code> output document is the exactly the
                same as the <code>data</code> input document. Consequently the debug processor can
                be easily inserted in a pipeline to log the XML data flow at a given point.
            </p>
            <img print-format="pdf" src="pages/processors-other-debug.png"/>
            <p>
                For instance, the processor can be called with:
            </p>
            <xml-source>
                <p:processor name="oxf:debug">
                    <p:input name="config">
                        <config>Employee</config>
                    </p:input>
                    <p:input name="data">
                        <employee>
                            <firstname>John</firstname>
                            <lastname>Smith</lastname>
                        </employee>
                    </p:input>
                    <p:output name="data" id="emp"/>
                </p:processor>
            </xml-source>
            <p>
                This will generate the message:
            </p>
            <source>Employee:

                &lt;employee>
                &lt;firstname>John&lt;/firstname>
                &lt;lastname>Smith&lt;/lastname>
                &lt;/employee></source>
            <p>
                Using <code>debug</code> attributes in pipelines is a shortcut for actually
                inserting the Debug processor in the pipeline: the Pipeline processor will insert a
                Debug processor when encountering <code>debug</code> attributes. By changing the
                <code>processors.xml</code> you can map the <code>oxf:debug</code> processor to your
                own "Debug processor" and this processor will be called when you use
                <code>debug</code> attributes in pipelines. If you decide to implement your own
                debug processor, note that it must have the same interface as the default Debug
                processor that comes with OPS.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="redirect-processor"/>
        <section>
            <title>Redirect Processor</title>
            <p>
                The Redirect Processor allows redirecting or forwarding the execution to a new URL:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Client-side</b> the browser is redirected to another URL. Typically, for
                        a Servlet environment, the <code>sendRedirect()</code> method is called on
                        the HTTP response object.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        If the redirection URL is an absolute path (e.g. <code>/hello</code>) then
                        it is interpreted as a path relative to the OPS Servlet context (i.e. if
                        your OPS WAR file is under <code>/ops</code>, then the resulting path is
                        <code>/ops/hello</code>). For other purposes, including redirecting to a
                        path within the same Servlet container but outside the OPS WAR context, you
                        have to use an absolute URL complete with scheme and host name.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p><b>Server-side</b>: a server-side forward is executed. Typically, for a
                    Servlet environment, the <code>forward</code> method is called on a Servlet
                    request dispatcher.</p>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                The processor's <code>data</code> input must conform to the following Relax NG
                schema:
            </p>
            <xml-source>
<element name="redirect-url" xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <interleave>
        <optional>
            <element name="server-side">
                <choice>
                    <value>true</value>
                    <value>false</value>
                </choice>
            </element>
        </optional>
        <element name="path-info">
            <text/>
        </element>
        <optional>
            <element name="parameters">
                <zeroOrMore>
                    <element name="parameter">
                        <element name="name">
                            <text/>
                        </element>
                        <oneOrMore>
                            <element name="value">
                                <text/>
                            </element>
                        </oneOrMore>
                    </element>
                </zeroOrMore>
            </element>
        </optional>
    </interleave>
</element>
            </xml-source>
            <p>
                The optional boolean <code>server-side</code> element determines whether a
                server-side forward is performed. The default is <code>false</code>.
            </p>
            <p>
                This example creates a processor that redirects the browser to
                <code>/login?user=jsmith</code>:
            </p>
            <xml-source>
                <p:processor name="oxf:redirect">
                    <p:input name="data">
                        <redirect-url>
                            <path-info>/login</path-info>
                            <parameters>
                                <parameter>
                                    <name>user</name>
                                    <value>jsmith</value>
                                </parameter>
                            </parameters>
                        </redirect-url>
                    </p:input>
                </p:processor>
            </xml-source>
            <note>
                <p>
                    It is recommended, whenever possible, to use the <link
                    href="reference-page-flow">Page Flow Controller</link> to perform page
                    redirections within a OPS application. The Page Flow Controller provides a much
                    higher-level abstraction of the notion of redirection than the Redirect
                    processor.
                </p>
            </note>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
