<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline" xmlns:xforms="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <header>
        <title>Other Generators</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>
                Generators are a special category of processors that have no XML data inputs, only
                outputs. They are generally used at the top of an XML pipeline to generate XML data
                from a Java object or other non-XML source. OPS provides several
                generators as described below. See also the <a
                href="processors-generators-url">URL</a> and <a
                href="processors-generators-request">Request</a> generators.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="scope-generator"/>
        <section>
            <title>Scope Generator</title>
            <section>
                <title>Introduction</title>
                <p>
                    The Scope generator can retrieve documents from the application, session and request
                    scopes. It can work together with the <a
                    href="processors-serializers#scope-serializer">Scope serializer</a>, or retrieve
                    documents stored by custom processors or other application modules.
                </p>
            </section>
            <p>
                The following Java object types are supported and checked in this order:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <b>org.dom4j.Document</b> - An XML document represented using the dom4j class
                    hierarchy.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>org.w3c.dom.Document</b> - An XML document represented using the W3C DOM
                    class hierarchy.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>java.lang.String</b> - An XML document represented as a String.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>java.lang.Object</b> - Any Java object. In this case, the object is
                    serialized to XML using <a href="http://www.castor.org">Castor</a>. An optional
                    <code>mapping</code> input may specify a custom <a
                    href="http://www.castor.org/xml-mapping.html">Castor mapping document</a>.
                </li>
            </ul>
            <section>
                <title>Inputs and Outputs</title>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Type</th>
                            <th>Name</th>
                            <th>Purpose</th>
                            <th>Mandatory</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="center">Input</td>
                            <td><code>config</code></td>
                            <td>Configuration</td>
                            <td align="center">Yes</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="center">Input</td>
                            <td><code>mapping</code></td>
                            <td>Castor XML mapping</td>
                            <td align="center">No</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="center">Output</td>
                            <td><code>data</code></td>
                            <td>Result XML data</td>
                            <td align="center">Yes</td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The <code>config</code> input has the following format:
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <config>
                        <key>cart</key>
                        <scope>application|session|request</scope>
                        <session-scope>application|portlet</session-scope>
                    </config>
                </xml-source>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>key</th>
                        <td>
                            The <code>&lt;key></code> element contains a string used to identify
                            the document. The same key must be used to store and retrieve a
                            document.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <th>scope</th>
                        <td>
                            <p>
                                The <code>&lt;scope></code> element specifies in what scope the
                                document is to be retrieved from. The available scopes are:
                            </p>
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    <b>application</b> - The application scope starts when the Web
                                    application is deployed. It ends when the Web application is
                                    undeployed. The application scope provides an efficient storage for
                                    data that does not need to be persisted and that is common for all
                                    users. It is typically used to cache information (e.g. configuration
                                    data for the application read from a database).
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    <b>session</b> - The session scope is attached to a given user of
                                    the Web application. It is typically used to store information that
                                    does not need to be persisted and is specific to a given user. It is
                                    typically used to cache the user's profile.
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    <b>request</b> - The request scope starts when an HTTP request is
                                    sent to the server. It ends when the corresponding HTTP response is
                                    sent back to the client. The request scope can be used to integrate
                                    a OPS application with legacy J2EE servlets.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <th>session-scope</th>
                        <td>
                            <p>
                                The <code>&lt;session-scope></code> element specifies in what
                                session scope the document is to be retrieved from. This element is
                                only allowed when the &lt;scope> element is set to
                                <code>session</code>. The available session scopes are:
                            </p>
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    <b>application</b> - access the entire application session. This
                                    is always a valid value.
                                </li>
                                <li>
                                    <b>portlet</b> - access the local portlet session. This is only
                                    valid if the processor is run hithin a portlet.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                            <p>
                                If the element is missing, a default value is used:
                                <code>application</code> when the processor runs within a servlet,
                                and <code>portlet</code> when the processor runs within a portlet.
                            </p>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
                <p>
                    The optional <code>mapping</code> input contains a custom <a
                    href="http://www.castor.org/xml-mapping.html">Castor mapping document</a>. This
                    mapping is used only if the object retrieved can only be handled as
                    <code>java.lang.Object</code> and not as one of the other types.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The <code>data</code> output contains the document retrieved. When the Scope
                    generator cannot find any document in scope for the given key, it returns a
                    "null document":
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <null xsi:nil="true"/>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
            <note>
                <p>
                    The Session generator, previously used to retrieve documents from the session
                    scope, is now deprecated. Use the Scope generator with session scope instead.
                </p>
            </note>
            <note>
                <p>
                    The Bean generator, previously used to retrieve JavaBeans from the request and
                    session scopes, is now deprecated. Use the Scope generator instead.
                </p>
            </note>
        </section>
        <a name="servletinclude"/>
        <section>
            <title>Servlet Include Generator</title>
            <p>
                The Servlet Include generator, using the <a
                href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/tomcat-4.1-doc/servletapi/javax/servlet/RequestDispatcher.html">RequestDispatcher</a>,
                calls and parses the result of another servlet running in the same Java virtual
                machine. The servlet can generate either XML or HTML. The generator automatically
                detects HTML and uses HTMLTidy to clean and parse the stream as XML.
            </p>
            <note>
                <p>
                    This generator works only in a servlet environment. It is not supported in portlets.
                </p>
            </note>
            <section>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <p>
                    The <code>config</code> input describes the servlet to call, and optionally
                    configures the HTMLTidy process. You can specify the servlet either by name or
                    path, and optionally specify a context path. The RelaxNG schema for this input
                    is the following:
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <element name="config" datatypeLibrary="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes"
                        xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
                        <interleave>
                            <choice>
                                <element name="servlet-name">
                                    <data type="string"/>
                                </element>
                                <element name="path">
                                    <data type="string"/>
                                </element>
                            </choice>
                            <optional>
                                <element name="context-uripath">
                                    <data type="string"/>
                                </element>
                            </optional>
                            <optional>
                                <element name="tidy-options">
                                    <interleave>
                                        <optional>
                                            <element name="show-warnings">
                                                <choice>
                                                    <value>true</value>
                                                    <value>false</value>
                                                </choice>
                                            </element>
                                            <optional>
                                                <element name="quiet">
                                                    <choice>
                                                        <value>true</value>
                                                        <value>false</value>
                                                    </choice>
                                                </element>
                                            </optional>
                                        </optional>
                                    </interleave>
                                </element>
                            </optional>
                        </interleave>
                    </element>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Data Output</title>
                <p>
                    The data output contains the result in the servlet include call.
                </p>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Example</title>
                <p>
                    This generator calls the <code>reports</code> servlet in the
                    <code>/admin</code> context path. Since this servlet is generating HTML, it's
                    better to have verbose error reporting from HTMLTidy.
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:processor name="oxf:servlet-include">
                        <p:input name="config">
                            <config>
                                <servlet-name>reports</servlet-name>
                                <context-path>/admin</context-path>
                                <tidy-options>
                                    <show-warnings>true</show-warnings>
                                    <quiet>false</quiet>
                                </tidy-options>
                            </config>
                        </p:input>
                        <p:output name="data" id="#report"/>
                    </p:processor>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
        </section>
        <a name="exception-generator"/>
        <section>
            <title>Exception Generator</title>
            <p>
                The Exception generator is usually used in an <link
               href="reference-error-pipeline">error pipeline</link>. It serializes to XML the data
               contained in a Java exception retrieved from the request scope, with the following
               information:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        All the exceptions, starting from the top-level exception down to the root
                        cause.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        For each exception, the exception class name, message, hierachy of location
                        information, and list of stack trace elements.
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                The following is an XML document resulting from an exception:
            </p>
            <xml-source>
                <exceptions>
                    <exception>
                        <type>org.orbeon.oxf.common.ValidationException</type>
                        <message>null, line 8, column 109, description xforms:bind element: Bind element is missing nodeset attribute null, line 8, column 109: Bind element is missing nodeset attribute</message>
                        <location>
                            <system-id/>
                            <line>8</line>
                            <column>109</column>
                            <description>xforms:bind element</description>
                            <element>&lt;xforms:bind xmlns:xforms="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms" id="xforms-element-2" ref="/instance/a" calculate=". + 1"/&gt;</element>
                        </location>
                        <location>
                            <system-id>oxf:/ops/pfc/xforms-epilogue.xpl</system-id>
                            <line>99</line>
                            <column>66</column>
                            <description>reading processor output</description>
                            <parameters>
                                <parameter>
                                    <name>name</name>
                                    <value>response</value>
                                </parameter>
                                <parameter>
                                    <name>id</name>
                                    <value>response</value>
                                </parameter>
                                <parameter>
                                    <name>ref</name>
                                    <value/>
                                </parameter>
                            </parameters>
                            <element>&lt;p:output xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline" name="response" id="response"/&gt;</element>
                        </location>
                        <location>
                            ...
                        </location>
                        ...
                        <stack-trace-elements>
                            <element>
                                <class-name>org.orbeon.oxf.common.ValidationException</class-name>
                                <method-name>wrapException</method-name>
                                <file-name>ValidationException.java</file-name>
                                <line-number>119</line-number>
                            </element>
                            ...
                        </stack-trace-elements>
                    </exception>
                    <exception>
                       ...
                    </exception>
                </exceptions>
            </xml-source>
            <p>
                A typical error pipeline should include an Exception generator followed by one or
                more transformation(s), and an HTML serializer.
            </p>
            <xml-source>
                <p:processor name="oxf:exception">
                    <p:output name="data" id="exception"/>
                </p:processor>
            </xml-source>
        </section>
        <a name="bean-generator"/>
        <section>
            <title>Bean Generator</title>
            <note>
                <p>
                    This processor is deprecated. Please refer to the <a
                    href="#scope-generator">Scope generator</a> instead.
                </p>
            </note>
            <p>
                The Bean generator serializes objects in the request or session to XML. If an object
                is a W3C Document (<code>org.w3c.dom.Document</code>), the XML for this document is
                sent as-is. Otherwise, the object is assumed to be a JavaBean and is serialized to
                XML with <link href="http://www.castor.org">Castor</link>. This generator takes
                two inputs:
            </p>
            <section>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <p>
                    The configuration input describes which bean to serialize, and two optional
                    sources. The sources can be <code>request</code>, <code>session</code> or both.
                    If both are specified, they are tried in order. In the example below, the
                    request is searched for the <code>guess</code> bean. If not found, the session
                    is tried.
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:input name="config">
                        <config>
                            <attribute>guess</attribute>
                            <source>request</source>
                            <source>session</source>
                        </config>
                    </p:input>
                </xml-source>
                <p>Here is the RelaxNG schema:</p>
                <xml-source>
                    <element name="config"
                        datatypeLibrary="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-datatypes"
                        xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">

                        <interleave>

                            <oneOrMore>
                                <element name="attribute">
                                    <data type="string"/>
                                </element>
                            </oneOrMore>

                            <interleave>
                                <optional>
                                    <element name="source">
                                        <value>request</value>
                                    </element>
                                </optional>
                                <optional>
                                    <element name="source">
                                        <value>session</value>
                                    </element>
                                </optional>
                            </interleave>

                        </interleave>

                    </element>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Mapping Input</title>
                <p>
                    This input specifies the Castor mapping file. See <link
                    href="http://www.castor.org/xml-mapping.html">Castor Documentation</link> for
                    more information on the mapping file. In most instances, the default mapping is
                    sufficient:
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:input name="mapping">
                        <mapping/>
                    </p:input>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Output</title>
                <p>
                    The output document contains a <code>beans</code> root node. Each serialized
                    bean is a child of the root node. The example above generates the following
                    document:
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <beans>
                        <guess useraguess="0">
                            <message>Hello</message>
                        </guess>
                    </beans>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
