<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline">
    <header>
        <title>Java Processor</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Rationale</title>
            <p>
                OPS comes with a number of pre-built processors. However, in some
                cases, it makes sense for the developer to write a new processor in Java. For the
                purpose of this discussion, let's assume that the processor is implemented in a file
                called <code>MyProcessor.java</code>. Custom processors can essentially be deployed
                in two ways:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>"Manually":
                    <ol>
                        <li>Compile <code>MyProcessor.java</code>.</li>
                        <li>Place the compiled class in
                        <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> (or in any other location where
                        it can be found by the classloader used to load the
                        classes in <code>ops.jar</code>).</li>
                        <li>Declare the new processor in
                        <code>processors.xml</code> (i.e. mapping an URI to this new
                        processor).</li>
                        <li>Use the newly declared processor in an XPL (OPS Pipeline Definition Language) file using the URI
                        declared in the <code>processors.xml</code>.</li>
                    </ol>
                </li>
                <br/>
                <li>Using the Java processor:
                    <ol>
                        <li>Place <code>MyProcessor.java</code> with the other
                        resources.</li>
                        <li>Use the new processor in an XPL file through the Java
                        processor. (We'll see below how this processor works in
                        detail.)</li>
                    </ol>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Benefits and Drawbacks</title>
            <p>The main advantages of using the Java processor versus manually
            compiling and deploying the compiled processor are:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Easy deployment: the Java file is placed with the
                other resources and one does not need to worry about
                compilation, packaging and deployment.</li>
                <li>Immediate visibility upon modifications: one can change
                the Java file, save it and instantly see the result in
                the browser (no need to compile, redeploy the
                application).</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                However, one should also note the drawbacks that come with the Java processor. In
                particular, the XML code needed in the XPL file to call a custom processor using the
                Java processor is a bit more complex than the XML code used to call a processor
                declared in <code>processors.xml</code>.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Usage</title>
            <img print-format="pdf" src="pages/processors-java-processor.png"/>
            <xml-source>
                <p:processor name="oxf:java">
                    <p:input name="config">
                        <config sourcepath="oxf:/java" class="MyProcessor"/>
                    </p:input>
                    <p:input name="data" href="..."/>
                    <p:output name="data" id="..."/>
                </p:processor>
            </xml-source>
            <table ca="|p{0.2\textwidth}|p{0.5\textwidth}|">
                <tr>
                    <th>config input</th>
                    <td>The <code>config</code> element has two attributes:
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                The optional <code>sourcepath</code> attribute points to the directory
                                containing the Java source in the resources. When omitted, the
                                default sourcepath is the directory of the pipeline calling the Java
                                processor (i.e. <code>sourcepath="."</code>). It is possible to use
                                the <code>file:</code> protocol and the <code>oxf:</code> protocol.
                                It is also possible to enter URLs relative to the location of the
                                calling pipeline, such as <code>sourcepath="."</code> (the default),
                                <code>sourcepath="../examples/java"</code>, etc.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <code>class</code> is the name of the Java class. The class has to implement the
                                <code>org.orbeon.oxf.processor.Processor</code> interface, as
                                described in the <link href="reference-processor-api">Processors
                                API</link>.
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                        <p>
                            Let's assume you place your Java source files in your resources
                            directory under the <code>java</code> subdirectory, and that the class
                            you want to use is <code>MyProcessor</code>, in the
                            <code>com.example</code> package. Consequently, you will have a file
                            <code>java/com/example/MyProcessor.java</code> in your resources. To use
                            this class, the Java processor config is: <code>&lt;config
                            sourcepath="oxf:/java" class="com.example.MyProcessor"/&gt;</code>.
                        </p>
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <th>Other inputs and outputs</th>
                    <td>The processor implemented in Java can take an
                    arbitrary number of inputs and outputs. The only
                    restriction on the inputs/outputs is that no input
                    can be named <code>config</code> as this input is
                    already used to configure the Java processor.</td>
                </tr>
            </table>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Compilation</title>
            <img print-format="pdf" src="pages/processors-java-process.png"/>
            <p>
                Before it can run a custom processor, the Java processor must
                compile the source code to generate the <code>class</code> files
                from the <code>java</code> files, and load those
                <code>class</code> files in the Java VM.
            </p>
            <p>
                By default, the Java processor uses Sun's compiler
                (<code>com.sun.tools.javac.Main</code>) to produce <code>class</code> files. See the
                <a href="reference-properties#java-compiler-class"><code>compiler-class</code></a>
                and <a href="reference-properties#java-compiler-jar"><code>compiler-jar</code></a>
                properties for more information about specifying the compiler to use.
            </p>
            <p>
                The <code>class</code> files are stored in the temporary directory, as defined by
                the Java system property <code>java.io.tmpdir</code>. Since compilation is a time
                consuming process, it is performed only when necessary. The Java processor compiles
                a custom processor when one of these conditions is met:
            </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        The source of the custom processor has never been compiled before.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The last modified date of the source file for the custom processor is prior
                        to the last modified date of the corresponding <code>class</code> file.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            <p>
                Note that Sun's <code>javac</code> automatically compiles all the files that the
                custom processor depends on, but that the Java processor only runs
                <code>javac</code> by comparing the dates of the <code>.java</code> and
                <code>class</code> of the custom processor itself. So if only one of the classes
                used by the custom processor has changed since the last compilation, the Java
                processor will not run the compiler. You should be aware of this limitation and
                "touch" the source of the custom processor when such a case occurs to force a
                compilation.
            </p>
            <p style="clear: both"/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Compilation Class Path</title>
            <p>
                Before invoking the Java compiler, OPS builds a classpath using two
                <link href="reference-properties#java-processor">properties</link>. The following
                list summaries the complete classpath order.

                <ol>
                    <li>
                        The class path defined by the <link
                        href="reference-properties#java-classpath"><code>classpath</code></link>
                        property.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The <code>WEB-INF/classes</code> directory, if found and Presentation
                        Server runs in an application server.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The JAR and ZIP files used by the classloader hierarchy that loaded the
                        Java processor. This automatically puts on the compilation class path the
                        classes that the Java processor can use.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        The JAR path defined by the <link
                        href="reference-properties#java-jarpath"><code>jarpath</code></link>
                        property.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        All the JAR and ZIP files under the <code>WEB-INF/lib</code> directory, if
                        found and OPS runs in an application server.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        If the <code>WEB-INF/lib</code> directory is not found, all the JAR and ZIP
                        files in the same directory as the JAR file containing the Java processor.
                        Typically, when running from a command line, this is the
                        <code>ops.jar</code> JAR file. If <code>ops.jar</code> is stored in a
                        directory with all the JAR files it depends on, those will automatically be
                        added to the compilation class path.
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Runtime Class Loading</title>
            <img print-format="pdf" src="pages/processors-java-classloader.png"/>
            <p>
                The compiled files are loaded by a class loader created by the Java processor. A
                different class loader is created for each source path, and all the classes in the
                same source path are loaded in the same class loader. For a given source path, a new
                class loader is created if one of these conditions is met:
            </p>
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li>No class loader has been previously created for this source path.</li>
                    <li>One of the classes in this source path has been compiled
                    since the class loader has been created.</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                When a new class loader is created, the previous one, if it exists, is discarded
                with all the loaded classes, and all the classes are re-loaded in the new class
                loader.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Limitations</title>
            <ul>
                <li>A custom processor used with the Java processor cannot use its
                <code>config</code> input, as this input is used to configure the Java
                processor.</li> <li>Java source files must be stored on the file system, i.e. the
                resources can only be loaded with the Filesystem or Web App <link
                href="reference-resource-managers">resource managers</link>. This is due to a
                limitation of Sun's <code>javac</code> which can only compile source files stored
                on disk.</li> <li>The Java processor will recompile a custom processor only if the
                Java source of the processor itself has changed. If only one of the classes (that
                the custom processor depends on) has changed since the last compilation, the source
                of the customer processor must be "touched" to force a re-compilation.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Properties</title>
            <p>
                Several global properties are relevant to the Java processor. Refer to the <a
                href="reference-properties#java-processor">Properties</a> section for more information.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Example</title>
            <p>
                The processor below declares a single output <code>data</code> and no inputs. It
                will always send the same XML content to its <code>data</code> output, namely an
                <code>answer</code> element containing the text "42". For more details on how to
                implement processors in Java, please refer to the <link
                href="reference-processor-api">Processors API</link>.
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[import org.orbeon.oxf.pipeline.api.PipelineContext;
import org.orbeon.oxf.processor.ProcessorInputOutputInfo;
import org.orbeon.oxf.processor.SimpleProcessor;
import org.xml.sax.ContentHandler;
import org.xml.sax.SAXException;
import org.xml.sax.helpers.AttributesImpl;

public class DeepThoughtProcessor extends SimpleProcessor {

    public DeepThoughtProcessor() {
        addOutputInfo(new ProcessorInputOutputInfo(OUTPUT_DATA));
    }

    public void generateData(PipelineContext context,
                             ContentHandler contentHandler)
            throws SAXException {
        String answer = "42";
        contentHandler.startDocument();
        contentHandler.startElement("", "answer", "answer", new AttributesImpl());
        contentHandler.characters(answer.toCharArray(), 0, answer.length());
        contentHandler.endElement("", "answer", "answer");
        contentHandler.endDocument();
    }
}
]]></source>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
