<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline">
    <header>
        <title>Email Processor</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <a name="email-processor"/>
        <section>
            <title>Scope</title>
            <p>
                The Email processor can send emails through an SMTP server (the usual way of
                sending emails). Its input contains the basic configuration (SMTP host, subject,
                etc.) as well as inline message body content. Alternatively, the message content can
                refer to external resources, such as resources on disk or dynamically generated
                content. It features the following high-level functionality:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <b>Multiple recipients:</b> send the same email to multiple recipients.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Multipart hierarchy:</b> it is possible to have multiple levels of multipart
                    messages.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Binary attachments:</b> binary files such as images and PDF files can be
                    attached to an email.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Dynamic attachments:</b> attachments can be generated dynamically. It is for
                    example possible to attach a dynamically generated chart or PDF file.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Data Input</title>
            <p>
                The <code>data</code> input contains the configuration of the processor as well
                as the message header and body. The following table describes the configuration
                elements:
            </p>
            <table>
                <tr>
                    <th>Name</th>
                    <th>Cardinality</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message</td>
                    <td>1</td>
                    <td>Root element</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/smtp-host</td>
                    <td>0..1</td>
                    <td>The SMTP host used to send the message</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/from</td>
                    <td>1</td>
                    <td>Sender of the message. Contains an <code>email</code> element and an optional <code>name</code> element.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/to</td>
                    <td>1..n</td>
                    <td>Recipient(s) of the message. Contains an <code>email</code> element and an optional <code>name</code> element.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/cc</td>
                    <td>0..n</td>
                    <td>Carbon copy recipient(s) of the message. Contains an <code>email</code> element and an optional <code>name</code> element.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/bcc</td>
                    <td>0..n</td>
                    <td>Blind carbon copy recipient(s) of the message. Contains an <code>email</code> element and an optional <code>name</code> element.</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/subject</td>
                    <td>1</td>
                    <td>Subject of the message</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/header</td>
                    <td>0..n</td>
                    <td>
                        Optional extra email header to add. Contains a <code>name</code> element
                        and a <code>value</code> element.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/body</td>
                    <td>1</td>
                    <td>Indicates a message body optionally containing multiple parts</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/body/@content-type</td>
                    <td>1</td>
                    <td>
                        The content-type of this body part. This attribute can also include a
                        <code>charset</code> attribute to specify a character encoding for text
                        types. For example: <code>text/plain; charset=utf-8</code>. This
                        attribute may also specify a multipart data type:
                        <code>multipart/mixed</code>, <code>multipart/alternative</code> or
                        <code>multipart/related</code>.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/body/part</td>
                    <td>0..n</td>
                    <td>
                        A message body part, if the body element specifies a multipart
                        <code>content-type</code> attribute.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/body/part/@name</td>
                    <td>1</td>
                    <td>The name of this body part</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/body/part@/content-type</td>
                    <td>1</td>
                    <td>
                        The content-type of this body part. This can also include a
                        <code>charset</code> attribute to specify a character encoding for text
                        types. For example: <code>text/plain; charset=utf-8</code>. This
                        attribute may also specify a multipart data type:
                        <code>multipart/mixed</code>, <code>multipart/alternative</code> or
                        <code>multipart/related</code>. In this case, the part contains an
                        embedded multipart message. This replaces the depreated
                        <code>mime-multipart</code> attribute.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/body/part@/content-disposition</td>
                    <td>0..1</td>
                    <td>
                        The optional Content-Disposition header of this body part. Not allowed
                        if the part contains embedded parts.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/body/part@/content-id</td>
                    <td>0..1</td>
                    <td>
                        The optional Content-ID header of this body part.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>message/body/part/*</td>
                    <td>1</td>
                    <td>
                        The content of the body part. This can contain embedded
                        <code>part</code> elements if the content is multipart. It can be XHTML
                        if the content-type is <code>text/html</code>. Finally, it can be any
                        text content, including just plain HTML (which can be embedded in a
                        CDATA section for convenience).
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Simple Messages</title>
            <p>
                A simple message requires a <code>body</code> element with:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>A text <code>content-type</code> attribute, for example <code>text/plain</code></li>
                <li>Text content</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                For example:
            </p>
            <xml-source>
                <p:processor name="oxf:email">
                    <p:input name="data">
                        <message>
                            <smtp-host>mail.example.org</smtp-host>
                            <from>
                                <email>trove@smith.com</email>
                                <name>Trove Smith</name>
                            </from>
                            <to>
                                <email>jani@smith.com</email>
                                <name>Jani Smith</name>
                            </to>
                            <subject>Reminder</subject>
                            <body content-type="text/plain">
                                Hello, Jani!
                            </body>
                        </message>
                    </p:input>
                </p:processor>
            </xml-source>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Character Encoding</title>
            <p>
                In the example above, no character encoding is specified for the
                <code>body</code> element. This determines what character encoding is used in
                the body of the email message constructed by the Email processor. If no
                encoding is specified, the default <code>iso-8859-1</code> is used. In some
                cases, it is useful to specify a character encoding. For example, if it is known
                that the message only contains ASCII characters, the <code>us-ascii</code>
                encoding can be specified. If, on the other hand, the message contains
                characters from multiple languages, the <code>utf-8</code> encoding can be
                specified.
            </p>
            <p>
                Use the <code>content-type</code> attribute to specify an encoding, for
                example: <code>content-type="text/plain; charset=utf-8"</code>.
            </p>
            <note>
                <p>
                    XML itself support Unicode, in other words it is designed to allow representing
                    all the characters specified by the Unicode specification. Those characters can
                    all be represented with the UTF-8 encoding. Because of this, the Email
                    processor could always encode text using the UTF-8 encoding. However, some mail
                    clients may not all support that encoding. It is therefore left to the user of
                    the Email processor to specify the appropriate encoding.
                </p>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Message Parts</title>
            <p>
                An email message can be composed of several parts. Parts can be used for:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <b>Attachments:</b> for example, a simple text message may have one of more
                    image attachments. Usually, the <code>multipart/mixed</code> content type
                    is used for this purpose.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Alternative Formats:</b> for example, both a plain text and an HTML
                    version of a same message may be sent. The recipient, or her mail software,
                    can then choose the most appropriate format to display. The
                    <code>multipart/alternative</code> content type is used for this purpose.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Dependencies:</b> for example, an HTML message may refer to images or
                    other resources embedded in the same email. The
                    <code>multipart/related</code> content type is used for this purpose.
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                To create a multipart email, specify one of the multipart content types on the
                <code>body</code> element. The <code>body</code> element must contain one or
                more <code>part</code> elements.
            </p>
            <p>
                In turn, <code>part</code> elements may contain other parts. In that case, a
                <code>part</code> element must declare a multipart content type attribute, and
                contain at least one <code>part</code> element.
            </p>
            <p>
                The main part of the body is encapsulated by the <code>body</code> element of
                the message.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Inline and Out of Line Parts</title>
            <p>
                The content of a part can be specified in two ways:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <b>Inline:</b> the content is directly embedded in the <code>body</code> or
                    <code>part</code> element.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Out of line:</b> the content is available from a resource or dynamically
                    generated.
                </li>
            </ul>
            <section>
                <title>Inline Parts</title>
                <p>
                    The content of the <code>body</code> or <code>part</code> element can be of
                    the following types:
                </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <b>HTML: </b> the content type is <code>text/html</code>. In this case,
                        the inline content is considered as HTML and converted to HTML. A root
                        <code>html</code> element must be present.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <b>Text type:</b> this is the case when the content type starts with
                        <code>text/</code>, for example <code>text/plain</code>. In thise case,
                        a character encoding can be specified as well.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <b>Binary Type:</b> for all other content types, the body of the part
                        must contain Base64-encoded binary data.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </section>
            <a name="out-of-line-parts"/>
            <section>
                <title>Out of Line Parts</title>
                <p>
                    This mode is enabled when the <code>part</code> element contains an
                    <code>src</code> attribute.
                </p>
                <p>
                    You can refer to a part content using a regular URI, for example:
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <part src="oxf:/image.jpg" content-type="image/jpeg"/>
                </xml-source>
                <p>
                    You can also refer to dynamically generated content by referring to <a
                    href="reference-xpl-pipelines#optional">optional processor inputs</a>. For
                    example:
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <part src="input:image-content" content-type="image/jpeg"/>
                </xml-source>
                <p>
                    In this case, the content of the image is obtained by reading the
                    <code>image-content</code> input of the Email processor. You can choose an
                    arbitray name for the input, as long as it is not <code>data</code>. Then,
                    connect a processor to the input, for example:
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:processor name="oxf:url-generator">
                        <p:input name="config">
                            <config>
                                <url>oxf:/image.jpg</url>
                                <content-type>image/jpeg</content-type>
                            </config>
                        </p:input>
                        <p:output name="data" id="file"/>
                    </p:processor>
                    <p:processor name="oxf:email">
                        <p:input name="data">
                            <message>
                                ...
                            </message>
                        </p:input>
                        <p:input name="image-content" href="#file"/>
                    </p:processor>
                </xml-source>
                <p>
                    When the content type of the input read is text (starts with
                    <code>text/</code>) or XML (<code>text/xml</code>,
                    <code>application/xml</code>, or ends with <code>+xml</code>), the input
                    document is expected to be in the text format specified by the <a
                    href="reference-formats#text-documents">text document format</a>. When the
                    content type of the input read is binary (all the other cases), the input
                    document is expected to be in the binary format specified by the <a
                    href="reference-formats#binary-documents">binary document format</a>.
                </p>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Properties</title>
            <p>
                Several global properties are relevant to the Email processor. Refer to the <a
                href="reference-properties#email-processor">Properties</a> section for more
                information.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Examples</title>
            <section>
                <title>Sending Alternative Parts</title>
                <p>
                    This example shows how to send both a text and HTML version of a message to
                    two recipients.
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:processor name="oxf:email">
                        <p:input name="data">
                            <message>
                                <smtp-host>mail.company.com</smtp-host>
                                <from>
                                    <email>trove@smith.com</email>
                                    <name>Trove Smith</name>
                                </from>
                                <to>
                                    <email>jani@smith.com</email>
                                    <name>Jani Smith</name>
                                </to>
                                <to>
                                    <email>tori@smith.com</email>
                                    <name>Tori Smith</name>
                                </to>
                                <subject>Reminder</subject>
                                <body mime-multipart="alternative">
                                    <part name="part1" content-type="text/plain">
                                      This is part 1
                                    </part>
                                    <part name="part2" content-type="text/html">
                                        <html>
                                            <body>
                                                <p>
                                                    This is part 2
                                                </p>
                                            </body>
                                        </html>
                                    </part>
                                </body>
                            </message>
                        </p:input>
                    </p:processor>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Related Parts and Attachments</title>
                <p>
                    This example shows how to send related parts with HTML, as well as
                    dynamically generated attachements.
                </p>
                <xml-source>
                    <p:processor name="oxf:email">
                        <p:input name="data">
                            <message>
                                <smtp-host>mail.company.com</smtp-host>
                                <from>
                                    <email>trove@smith.com</email>
                                    <name>Trove Smith</name>
                                </from>
                                <to>
                                    <email>jani@smith.com</email>
                                    <name>Jani Smith</name>
                                </to>
                                <subject>Email Example</subject>
                                <body mime-multipart="alternative">
                                    <comment> Provide simple text alternative </comment>
                                    <part name="text" content-type="text/plain">This is some important message body.</part>
                                    <comment> HTML alternative </comment>
                                    <part name="html" content-type="multipart/related">
                                        <part name="main" content-type="text/html">
                                            <html>
                                                <head>
                                                    <title>Email Example</title>
                                                </head>
                                                <body>
                                                    <p style="border: dotted 1px gray; padding: 5px">This is some <em>important</em> message body.</p>
                                                    <p>
                                                        This is a static image attached to the email and referred to by the HTML version:
                                                    </p>
                                                    <div style="border: dotted 1px gray; padding: 5px">
                                                        <img src="cid:id1"/>
                                                    </div>
                                                    <p>
                                                        This is an dynamic chart image attached to the email and referred to by the HTML version:
                                                    </p>
                                                    <div style="border: dotted 1px gray; padding: 5px">
                                                        <img src="cid:id2"/>
                                                    </div>
                                                </body>
                                            </html>
                                        </part>
                                        <comment> Attachments </comment>
                                        <part name="image" content-type="image/gif" content-disposition="inline; filename=&quot;logo.gif&quot;" content-id="id1" src="oxf:/logo.gif"/>
                                        <part name="chart" content-type="image/png" content-disposition="inline; filename=&quot;chart.png&quot;" content-id="id2" src="input:png-document"/>
                                        <part name="pdf" content-type="application/pdf" content-disposition="inline; filename=&quot;report.pdf&quot;" src="input:pdf-document"/>
                                    </part>
                                </body>
                            </message>
                        </p:input>
                        <p:input name="png-document"/>
                        <p:input name="pdf-document"/>
                    </p:processor>
                </xml-source>
            </section>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
