<!--
    Copyright (C) 2004 Orbeon, Inc.

    The Orbeon documentation is not distributed under the LGPL license. Use of the documentation is
    subject to the following terms:

    * Conversion to other formats is allowed, but the actual content may not be altered or edited
      in any way.

    * You may create printed copies for your own personal use.

    * For all other uses, such as selling printed copies or using (parts of) the manual in another
      publication, prior written agreement from Orbeon, Inc. is required.

    Please contact Orbeon at info@orbeon.com for more information.
-->
<document xmlns:p="http://www.orbeon.com/oxf/pipeline" xmlns:xforms="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <header>
        <title>Non-XML Documents in XPL</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>
                In OPS <a href="reference-xpl-pipelines">XPL and pipelines</a> only
                deal with XML documents. This means that between processor outputs and processor
                inputs in a pipeline, only pure XML infosets circulate. There is however often a
                need to handle non-XML data in pipelines, in particular:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <b>Binary document:</b> any document that can be represented as a stream of
                    bytes. In general this is the case of any document, but some document formats
                    are almost always represented this way: images, sounds, PDF documents, etc.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <b>Text documents:</b> any document that can be represented as a stream of
                    characters. Some documents are better looked at this way, like plain txt files,
                    HTML files, and even the textual representation of XML.
                </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                OPSs addresses this question by defining two standard XML document
                formats to embed binary and text documents within an XML infoset. This solution has
                the benefit of keeping XPL simple by limiting it to pure XML infosets, while
                allowing XPL to conveniently manipulate any binary and text document.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="binary-documents"/>
        <section>
            <title>Binary Documents</title>
            <p>
                A binary document consist of a <code>document</code> root node containing
                character data encoded with Base64. An <code>xsi:type</code> attribute is also
                present, as well as an optional <code>content-type</code> attribute, for
                example:
            </p>
            <xml-source>
<document xsi:type="xs:base64Binary" content-type="image/jpeg">
/9j/4AAQSkZJRgABAQEBygHKAAD/2wBDAAQDAwQDAwQEBAQFBQQFBwsHBwYGBw4KCggLEA4R
...
KKACiiigAooooAKKKKACiiigAooooAKKKKACiiigAooooAKKKKACiiigAooooA//2Q==
</document>
            </xml-source>
            <note>
                <p>
                    For the curious, the Base64 encoding is documented in <a
                    href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2045.txt">RFC 2045</a>. This encoding represents
                    binary data by mapping it to a set of 64 ASCII characters.
                </p>
            </note>
            <p>
                Such documents are not meant to be read by users, in the same way that regular
                binary files are not meant to be examined by users. Binary documents are generated
                by OPS processors, like the <a
                href="processors-generators-url">URL generator</a> and <a
                href="processors-converters">converters</a>. They are consumed by processors like
                the <a href="processors-serializers-http">HTTP serializer</a>, the <a
                href="processors-messaging-email">Email processor</a>, and <a
                href="processors-converters">converters</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
        <a name="text-documents"/>
        <section>
            <title>Text Documents</title>
            <p>
                A text document consists of a <code>document</code> root element containing the
                text. An <code>xsi:type</code> attribute is also present, as well as an optional
                <code>content-type</code> attribute:
            </p>
            <xml-source>
<document xsi:type="xs:string" content-type="text/plain">
    This is line one of the input document!
    This is line two of the input document!
    This is line three of the input document!
</document>
            </xml-source>
            <p>
                The <code>content-type</code> attribute may have a <code>charset</code> parameter
                providing a hint for the character encoding, for example:
            </p>
            <xml-source>
<document xsi:type="xs:string" content-type="text/plain; charset=iso-8859-1">
    This is line one of the input document!
    This is line two of the input document!
    This is line three of the input document!
</document>
            </xml-source>
            <p>
                Because XML character data itself is represented in Unicode (in other words it is
                designed to allow representing in a same document all the characters specified by
                the Unicode specification), there is no requirement for specifying character
                encoding in XML pipelines. However, when an XML infoset is read or written as an
                textual XML document, specifying a character encoding may may be a useful hint. For
                example a URL generator can, with this mechanism, communicate to an HTTP serializer
                the preferred character encoding obtained when the document was read. The serializer
                may then use that hint, but it is by no means authoritative.
            </p>
            <p>
                In general, XML documents can be read and written using the <code>utf-8</code>
                character encoding, which allows representing all the Unicode characters. However,
                when dealing with other types of text documents, tools such as text editors may not
                be able to deal correctly with <code>utf-8</code>. In such cases, it can be useful
                to use even more widespread character encodings such as <code>iso-8859-1</code> or
                <code>us-ascii</code>. The drawback is that such encodings allow representing a much
                smaller set of characters than <code>utf-8</code>.
            </p>
            <p>
                Unlike binary documents, text documents can easily be examined by users. They can
                also be easily manipulated by languages such as <a href="processors-xslt">XSLT</a>.
                Like binary documents, they are generated by OPS processors, like
                the <a href="processors-generators-url">URL generator</a> and <a
                href="processors-converters">converters</a>. They are consumed by processors like
                the <a href="processors-serializers-http">HTTP serializer</a>, the <a
                href="processors-messaging-email">Email processor</a>, and <a
                href="processors-converters">converters</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Streaming</title>
            <p>
                Processors can stream binary and text documents by issuing a number of short
                character SAX events. It is therefore possible to generate "infinitely" long binary
                and text documents with a constant amount of memory, assuming both the sender and
                the receiver of the document are able to perform streaming. This is the case for
                example of the <a href="processors-generators-url">URL generator</a> and
                the <a href="processors-serializers-http">HTTP serializer</a>.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
