<!--
    Copyright (C) 2006 Orbeon, Inc.
  
    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the
    GNU Lesser General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version
    2.1 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  
    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY;
    without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
    See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details.
  
    The full text of the license is available at http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html
-->
<example-descriptor>
    <title>DMV Forms Example</title>
    <xi:include href="example-descriptor-files.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    <description xmlns:f="http://orbeon.org/oxf/xml/formatting">
        <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
            <img src="/examples/forms/images/dmv-forms-logo.png" alt="DMV" align="right"/>
            <p>
                The DMV Forms example illustrates some of the best practices of XForms and Orbeon
                Presentation Server to create web forms by leveraging a real-life example. Among
                other things, it tackles:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Using XForms to capture and display form data.</b> XForms was designed
                        primarily to replace HTML forms, and of course it shines at capturing and
                        displaying form data. In this example, we illustrate how to use XForms
                        control to capture simple text data, dates, and flags.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Using XML Schema to validate form data.</b> Data validation is a strong
                        requirement of online forms. By using XForms's XML Schema support, you can
                        write validation constraints once and use them both on the client and on
                        the server. We also show how you can use other XForms constraints for
                        example to ensure that certain fields are required.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Using XForms to retrieve and save data from XML services.</b> XForms is
                        fully XML-aware, not only in its syntax, but in the way it communicates with
                        the external world. This example retrieves and stores data through XML
                        services thanks to the XForms submission facilities.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Repeating homogeneous data sections.</b> Repeated sections are common in
                        forms. In this example we show how you can easily insert new rows and delete
                        existing rows in a repeated section, using <code>xforms:repeat</code>,
                        <code>xforms:insert</code> and <code>xforms:delete</code>, while controlling
                        the minimal and maximal number of rows.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Producing forms in formats such as HTML, XML or PDF.</b> Storing form
                        data in XML format makes it easy to exchange between systems. This example
                        allows you to easily look at the resulting XML document. It also features a
                        full template-based PDF export, which allows you to print an official
                        resulting form. The PDF facilities are available in Orbeon
                        PresentationServer.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Implementing XML services.</b> Many technologies and platforms can be
                        used to implement services. Orbeon PresentationServer does not focus on
                        services but on the presentation, however, we show how you can quickly
                        implement XML services with OPS's Page Flow Controler, XPL and the eXist
                        XML database,
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Navigating between pages.</b> XForms pages rarely exist in a vacuum, and
                        are often part of a flow of pages. Here we show how you can easily go back
                        and forth between a summary and detail page while passing information in the
                        process using the OPS Page Flow Controller and XForms facilities such as
                        <code>xforms:load</code>.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        <b>Externalizing resources.</b> In order to facilitate maintenance and
                        localization, externalizing text resources is often a good idea if not a
                        must. We show how easy it is to do this with XForms so as to be fully
                        prepared to localize your application.
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </div>
    </description>
</example-descriptor>
